Iron Heinrich (1812)

Once upon a time there was a princess who went out into a forest and satpassive, female, neutral next to a cool well.

She took great pleasure in throwing a golden ballactive, female, eager into the air and catchingactive, female, eager it, but once it went too high. She held out heractive, female, eager hand with her fingers curved to catch it, but it fell to the ground and rolled and rolled right into the water.

Horrifiednegative, female, the princess followed it with her eyespassive, female, neutral, but the well was so deep that she could not see its bottom.

Then she began to crypassive, female, neutral bitterlynegative, female, I'd give anything, if only I could get my ball back: my clothes, my precious stones, my pearls, anything in the world.

At this a frog stuck his headactive, female, neutral out of the water and said, "Princess, why are you cryingpassive, female, neutral so bitterlynegative, female?"

"Oh," she said, "you uglynegative, male frog, how can you help me? My golden ball has fallen into the well."

The frog said, "I do not want your pearls, your precious stones, and your clothes, but if you'll accept me as a companion and let me sit next to you and eat from your plate and sleep in your bed, and if you'll love and cherish me, then I'll bring your ballactive, male, hesitant back to you."

The princess thought, "What is this stupidnegative, male frog trying to say? After all, he does have to stay here in the water. But still, maybe he can get my ball. I'll go ahead and say yes," and she said aloudactive, female, hesitant, "Yes, for all I care. Just bring me back my golden ball, and I'll promise everything."

The frog stuck his head under the wateractive, male, eager and doveactive, male, eager to the bottom.

He returned a short time later with the golden ball in his mouth and threw it onto the landactive, male, eager.

When the princess saw her ball once again, she rushed toward itactive, female, eager, picked it upactive, female, eager, and was so happypositive, female to have it in her hand again, that she could think of nothing else than to run homeactive, female, eager with it.

The frog called after heractive, male, eager, "Wait, princess, take me with you like you promised," but she paid no attention to him.

The next day the princess was sitting at her tablepassive, female, neutral when she heard something coming up the marble steps: plip, plop. Then there came a knockactive, male, eager at the door, and a voice called out, "Princess, youngestpositive, female, open the door for me!"

She ranactive, female, eager and opened the dooractive, female, eager. It was the frog, whom she had put completely out of her mind. Frightenednegative, female, she slammedactive, female, eager the door shut and returnedpassive, female, eager to the table. The king saw that her heart was pounding and asked, "Why are you afraid?"

"There is a disgustingnegative, positive frog out there," she said, "who got my golden ball out of the water. I promisedpassive, female, hesitant him that he could be my companion, but I didn't think that he could leave his water, but now he is just outside the door and wants to come in."

Just then there came a second knockactive, male, eager at the door, and a voice calledactive, male, eager out: Youngestpositive, female daughter of the king, Open up the door for me, Don't you know what yesterday, You said to me down by the well? Youngestpositive, female daughter of the king, Open up the door for me.

The king said, "What you have promised, you must keep. Go and let the frog in."

She went and openedactive, female, hesistant the door, and the frog hopped in, then followedactive, male, neutral her up to her chair. After she had sat down againpassive, female, neutral, he called outactive, male, eager, "Lift me up next to you."

The princess did not want to, but the king commandedactive, male, neutral her to do it. When the frog was seated next to her he said, "Now pushpassive, female, hesitant your golden plate closer. I want to eat from it."

She had to do this as well. When he had eatenpassive, male, eager all he wanted, he said, "Now I am tired and want to sleep. Take me to your room, make your bed, so that we can lie in it together."

The princess was horrifiednegative, female when she heard that. She was afraidnegative, female of the cold frog and did not dare to even touch him, and yet he was supposed to lie next to her in her bed; she began to crypassive, female, neutral and didn't want to at all.

The king became angryactive, male, neutral and commanded heractive, male, neutral to do what she had promised.

There was no helping it; she had to do what her father wanted, but in her heart she was bitterly angrynegative, female. She picked up the frogactive, female, hesitant with two fingers, carried himactive, female, hesitant to her room, and climbed into bedactive, female, hesitant, but instead of laying him next to herself, she threw himactive, female, eager bang! against the wall. "Now you will leave me in peace, you disgustingnegative, male frog!"

But when the frog came down onto the bed, he was a handsomepositive, male youngpositive, male prince, and he was her dearpositive, male companion, and she held him in esteempositive, male as she had promised, and they fell asleep together with pleasure.

The next morning the prince's faithfulpositive, male Heinrich arrived in a splendid carriage drawn by eight horses, decorated with feathers and glistening with gold. He had been so saddenednegative, male by the prince's transformation that he had had to place three iron bands around his heart to keep it from bursting in sorrow. The prince climbedactive, male, neutral into the carriage with the princess. His faithful servant stoodpassive, male, eager at the rear to drive them to his kingdom. After they had gone a short distance, the prince heard a crack from behind, as though something had broken.

He turned around and said, "Heinrich, the carriage is breaking apart."

No, my lord, the carriage it's not, But one of the bands surrounding my heart, That suffered such great pain, When you were sitting in the well, When you were a frog.

Once again, and then once again the prince heard a cracking sound and thought that the carriage was breaking apart, but it was the bands springing from faithfulpositive, male Heinrich's heart because his master was now redeemed and happy.

Iron Heinrich (1857)

In olden times, when wishing still did some good, there lived a king whose daughters were all beautifulpositive, female, but the youngest was so beautifulpositive, female that the sun itself, who, indeed, has seen so much, marveled every time it shone upon her face. In the vicinity of the king's castle there was a large, dark forest, and in this forest, beneath an old linden tree, there was a well. In the heat of the day the princess would go out into the forest and sitpassive, female, eager on the edge of the cool well. To pass the time she would take a golden ball, throwactive, female, neutral it into the air, and then catchactive, female, neutral it. It was her favorite plaything.

Now one day it happened that the princess's golden ball did not fall into her hands, that she held up high, but instead it fell to the ground and rolled right into the water. The princess followedpassive, female, neutral it with her eyes, but the ball disappeared, and the well was so deep that she could not see its bottom. Then she began to crypassive, female, neutral. She criedpassive, female, neutral louder and louder, and she could not console herself.

As she was thus lamentingpassive, female, neutral, someone called out to her, "What is the matter with you, princess? Your crying would turn a stone to pity."

She lookedactive, female, neutral around to see where the voice was coming from and saw a frog, who had stuck his thick, ugly head out of the water. "Oh, it's you, old water-splasher," she said. "I am crying because my golden ball has fallen into the well."

"Be still and stop crying," answered the frog. I can helpactive, male, hesitant you, but what will you give me if I bring back your plaything?"

"Whatever you want, dear frog," she saidactive, female, neutral, "my clothes, my pearls and precious stones, and even the golden crown that I am wearing."

The frog answeredactive, male, neutral, "I do not want your clothes, your pearls and precious stones, nor your golden crown, but if you will loveactive, male, eager me and acceptactive, male, eager me as a companion and playmate, and let me sitpassive, male, eager next to you at your table and eatactive, male, eager from your golden plate and drinkactive, male, eager from your cup and sleeppassive, male, eager in your bed, if you will promiseactive, male, neutral this to me, then I'll diveactive, male, hesitant down and bring your golden ball back to you."

"Oh, yes," she said, "I promiseactive, female, eager all of that to you if you will just bring the ball back to me." But she thoughtpassive, female, hesitant, "What is this stupidnegative, male frog trying to say? He just sitspassive, male, neutral here in the water with his own kind and croakspassive, male, neutral. He cannot be a companion to a human."

As soon as the frog heardpassive, male, neutral her say "yes" he stuckactive, male, eager his head under and doveactive, male, eager to the bottom. He paddledactive, male, neutral back up a short time later with the golden ball in his mouth and threwactive, male, neutral it onto the grass. The princess was filledpassive, female, eager with joy when she saw her beautiful plaything once again, picked it up, and ran off.

"Wait, wait," calledactive, male, eager the frog, "take me along. I cannot run as fast as you." But what did it help him, that he croakedactive, male, neutral out after her as loudly as he could? She paid no attention to him, but instead hurriedactive, female, eager home and soon forgotpassive, female, neutral the poor frog, who had to return again to his well.

The next day the princess was sittingpassive, female, neutral at the table with the king and all the people of the court, and was eatingactive, female, neutral from her golden plate when something came creeping up the marble steps: plip, plop, plip, plop. As soon as it reached the top, there came a knockactive, male, eager at the door, and a voice called out, "Princess, youngestpositive, female, open the door for me!"

She ranactive, female, eager to see who was outside. She openedactive, female, eager the door, and the frog was sittingpassive, male, neutral there. Frightenednegative, female, she slammedactive, female, eager the door shut and returnedpassive, female, eager to the table. The king saw that her heart was pounding and asked, "My child, why are you afraidnegative, female? Is there a giant outside the door who wants to get you?"

"Oh, no," she answered. "it is a disgustingnegative, male frog."

"What does the frog want from you?"

"Oh, father dear, yesterday when I was sitting near the well in the forest and playingpassive, female, neutral, my golden ball fell into the water. And because I was crying passive, female, neutralso much, the frog brought it back, and because he insisted, I promisedactive, female, hesitant him that he could be my companion, but I didn't think that he could leave his water. But now he is just outside the door and wants to come in."

Just then there came a second knockactive, male, eager at the door, and a voice calledactive, male, eager out: Youngestpositive, female daughter of the king, Open up the door for me, Don't you know what yesterday, You said to me down by the well? Youngestpositive, female daughter of the king, Open up the door for me.

The king said, "What you have promised, you must keep. Go and let the frog in."

She went and openedactive, female, hesistant the door, and the frog hopped in, then followedactive, male, neutral her up to her chair. He satpassive, male, neutral there and calledpassive, male, neutral out, "Lift me up next to you."

She hesitated, until finally the king commandedactive, male, hesitant her to do it. When the frog was seated next to her he said, "Now pushpassive, female, hesitant your golden plate closer, so we can eat together."

She did it, but one could see that she did not want to. The frog enjoyedpassive, male, eager his meal, but for her every biteactive, female, hesitant stuck in her throat. Finally he said, "I have eaten all I want and am tired. Now carry me to your room and make your bed so that we can go to sleep."

The princess began to crypassive, female, neutral and was afraid of the cold frog and did not dare to even touch him, and yet he was supposed to sleep in her beautiful, clean bed.

The king became angryactive, male, neutral and said, "You should not despise someone who has helped you in time of need."

She picked him upactive, female, hesitant with two fingers, carriedactive, female, hesitant him upstairs, and setpassive, female, hesitant him in a corner. As she was lying in bedpassive, female, hesitant, he came creepingactive, male, neutral up to her and said, "I am tired, and I want to sleep as well as you do. Pick me up or I'll tell your father."

With that she became bitterly angry and threw him against the wallactive, female, eager with all her might. "Now you will have your peace, you disgustingnegative, male frog!"

But when he fell down, he was not a frog, but a prince with beautifulpositive, male friendlypositive, male eyes. And he was now, according to her father's will, her dear companion and husband. He told her how he had been enchanted by a wicked witch, and that she alone could have rescued himactive, female, neutral from the well, and that tomorrow they would go together to his kingdom. Then they fell asleep.

The next morning, just as the sun was waking them, a carriage pulled up, drawn by eight horses. They had white ostrich feathers on their heads and were outfitted with chains of gold. At the rear stood the young king's servant, faithful Heinrich. Faithful Heinrich had been so saddened by his master's transformationpassive, male, neutral into a frog that he had had to place three iron bands around his heart to keep it from bursting in grief and sorrow. The carriage was to take the king back to his kingdom. Faithfulpositive, male Heinrich liftedactive, male, eager them both inside and took his place at the rear. He was filled with joy over the redemption. After they had gone a short distance, the prince heard a crack from behind, as though something had broken.

He turned around and said, "Heinrich, the carriage is breaking apart."

No, my lord, the carriage it's not, But one of the bands surrounding my heart, That suffered such great pain, When you were sitting in the well, When you were a frog.

Once again, and then once again the prince heard a cracking sound and thought that the carriage was breaking apart, but it was the bands springing from faithfulpositive, male Heinrich's heart because his master was now redeemed and happy.

Little Red Cap (1857)

Once upon a time there was a sweetpositive, female littleneutral, female girl. Everyone who saw her liked her, but most of all her grandmother, who did not know what to give the child next. Once she gave her a little cap made of red velvetactive, female, eager. Because it suited her so well, and she wanted to wear it all the time, she came to be known as Little Red Cappassive, female, neutral.

One day her mother said to her, "Come Little Red Cap. Here is a piece of cake and a bottle of wine. Take them to your grandmother. She is sicknegative, female and weaknegative, female, and they will do her well. Mind your manners and give her my greetings. Behave yourself on the way, and do not leave the path, or you might fall down and break the glass, and then there will be nothing for your grandmother. And when you enter her parlor, don't forget to say 'Good morning,' and don't peer into all the corners first."

"I'll do everything just right," said Little Red Cap, shaking her mother's handactive, female, eager.

The grandmother lived out in the woods, a half hour from the village. When Little Red Cap entered the woods a wolf came up to her. She did not know what a wickednegative, male animal he was, and was not afraid of himpassive, female, neutral.

"Good day to you, Little Red Cap."

"Thank you, wolf."

"Where are you going so early, Little Red Cap?"

"To grandmother's."

"And what are you carrying under your apron?"

"Grandmother is sicknegative, female and weaknegative, female, and I am taking her some cake and wineactive, female, eager. We baked yesterday, and they should be good for her and give her strength."

"Little Red Cap, just where does your grandmother live?"

"Her house is good quarter hour from here in the woods, under the three large oak trees. There's a hedge of hazel bushes there. You must know the place," said Little Red Cap.

The wolf thought to himself, "Now that sweetpositive, female young thing is a tasty bite for me. She will taste even better than the old woman. You must be slynegative, male, and you can catch them both."

He walked along a little while with Little Red Cap, then he said, "Little Red Cap, just look at the beautiful flowers that are all around us. Why don't you go and take a look? And I don't believe you can hear how beautifully the birds are singing. You are walking along as though you were on your way to school. It is very beautiful in the woods."active, male, eager

Little Red Cap opened her eyes and when she saw the sunbeams dancing to and fro through the trees and how the ground was covered with beautiful flowers, she thought, "If a take a fresh bouquet to grandmother, she will be very pleased. Anyway, it is still early, and I'll be home on time." And she ran off the path into the woods looking for flowers. Each time she picked one she thought that she could see an even more beautiful one a little way off, and she ran after it, going further and further into the woodsactive, female, eager. But the wolf ran straight to the grandmother's house and knocked on the dooractive, male, eager.

"Who's there?"

"Little Red Cap. I'm bringing you some cake and wineactive, male, eager. Open the door."

"Just press the latch," called out the grandmother. "I'm too weaknegative, female to get up."

The wolf pressed the latch, and the door opened. He stepped inside, went straight to the grandmother's bed, and ate her up. Then he put on her clothes, put her cap on his head, got into her bed, and pulled the curtains shutactive, male, eager.

Little Red Cap had run after the flowers. After she had gathered so many that she could not carry any more, she remembered her grandmother, and then continued on her way to her houseactive, female, neutral. She found, to her surprise, that the door was open. She walked into the parlor, and everything looked so strange that she thought, "Oh, my God, why am I so afraid? I usually like it at grandmother's."active, female, hesitant

She called out, "Good morning!"active, female, neutral but received no answerpassive, female, neutral.

Then she went to the bed and pulled back the curtainsactive, female, hesitant. Grandmother was lying there with her cap pulled down over her face and looking very strangenegative, female.passive, female, neutral

"Oh, grandmother, what big ears you haveneutral, male!"

"All the better to hear you with."

"Oh, grandmother, what big eyes you haveneutral, male!"

"All the better to see you with."

"Oh, grandmother, what big hands you haveneutral, male!"

"All the better to grab you with!"

"Oh, grandmother, what a horribly big mouth you havenegative, male!"

"All the better to eat you with!"

The wolf had scarcely finished speaking when he jumped from the bed with a single leap and ate up poornegative, female Little Red Cap. As soon as the wolf had satisfied his desires, he climbed back into bed, fell asleep, and began to snore very loudlyactive, male, eager.

A huntsman was just passing by. He thought, "The oldneutral, female woman is snoring so loudlypassive, female, neutral. You had better see if something is wrong with herpassive, male, eager."

He stepped into the parlor, and when he approached the bed, he saw the wolf lying there. "So here I find you, you oldneutral, male sinnernegative, male," he said.active, male, eager "I have been hunting for you a long timeactive, male, eager."

He was about to aim his rifle when it occurred to him that the wolf might have eaten the grandmother, and that she still might be rescued. So instead of shooting, he took a pair of scissors and began to cut open the wolf's bellyactive, male, eager. After a few cuts he saw the red cap shining through., and after a few more cuts the girl jumped out, crying, "Oh, I was so frightened! It was so dark inside the wolf's body!"passive, female, eager

And then the grandmother came out as well, alive but hardly able to breathepassive, female, neutral. Then Little Red Cap fetched some large stones. She filled the wolf's body with themactive, female, eager, and when he woke up and tried to run away, the stones were so heavy that he immediately fell down deadpassive, male, neutral.

The three of them were happy. The huntsman skinned the wolf and went home with the peltactive, male, eager. The grandmother ate the cake and drank the wine that Little Red Cap had broughtactive, female, eager. And Little Red Cap thought, "As long as I live, I will never leave the path and run off into the woods by myself if mother tells me not toactive, female, eager."

They also tell how Little Red Cap was taking some baked things to her grandmother another time, when another wolf spoke to her and wanted her to leave the pathactive, male, eagerpassive, female, eager. But Little Red Cap took care and went straight to grandmother'sactive, female, eager. She told her that she had seen the wolf, and that he had wished her a good day, but had stared at her in a wicked manner. "If we hadn't been on a public road, he would have eaten me uppassive, female, neutral," she said.

"Come," said the grandmother. "Let's lock the door, so he can't get inactive, female, eager."

Soon afterward the wolf knocked on the door and called out, "Open up, grandmother. It's Little Red Cap, and I'm bringing you some baked things."active, male, eager

They remained silent, and did not open the dooractive, female, eager. Gray-Head crept around the house several times, and finally jumped onto the roof. He wanted to wait until Little Red Cap went home that evening, then follow her and eat her up in the darknessactive, male, eager. But the grandmother saw what he was up to. There was a large stone trough in front of the house.

"Fetch a bucket, Little Red Cap," she said to the child. "Yesterday I cooked some sausage. Carry the water that I boiled them with to the trough." Little Red Cap carried water until the large, large trough was clear fullactive, female, eager. The smell of sausage arose into the wolf's nose. He sniffed and looked down, stretching his neck so long that he could no longer hold himself, and he began to slide.active, male, eager He slid off the roof, fell into the trough, and drownedpassive, male, neutral. And Little Red Cap returned home happilyactive, female, eager, and no one harmed her.

Rapunzel (1812)

Once upon a time there was a man and a woman who had long wished for a child but had never received one.

Finally, however, the woman came to be with child.passive, mixed, eager

Through the small rear window of these people's house they could see into a fairy'spositive, female garden that was filled with flowers and herbs of all kinds.

No one dared enter this garden.

One day the woman was standing at this window, and she saw the most beautiful rapunzel in a bed.

She longed for some, but not knowing how to get any, she became miserably ill.passive, female, hesitant

Her husband was frightenednegative, male, and asked her why she was doing so poorly.

"Oh, if I do not get some rapunzel from the garden behind our house, I shall surely die," she said.

The man, who loved her dearly, decided to get her some, whatever the cost.active, male, eager

One evening he climbed over the high wall, hastily dug up a handful of rapunzel, and took it to his wife.active, male, eager

She immediately made a salad from it, which she devoured greedily.negative, female

It tasted so very good to her that by the next day her desire for more had grown threefold.

The man saw that there would be no peace, so once again he climbed into the garden.active, male, eager

To his horror, the fairypositive, female was standing there.

She scolded him fiercelyactive, female, eager for daring to enter and steal from her garden.

He excused himself as best he could with his wife's pregnancy, and how it would be dangerous to deny her anything.passive, male, eager

Finally the fairypositive, female spoke, "I will accept your excuse and even allow you to take as much rapunzel as you want, if you will give me the child that your wife is now carrying."negative, female

In his fear the man agreed to everything.passive, male, neutral

When the woman gave birth, the fairypositive, female appeared, named the littleneutral, female girl Rapunzel, and took her away.active, female, eager

This Rapunzel became the most beautiful childpositive, female under the sun, but when she was twelve years old, the fairypositive, female locked her in a high tower that had neither a door nor a stairway, but only a tiny little window at the very top.active, female, eager

When the fairypositive, female wanted to enter, she stood below and called out:active, female, eager

Rapunzel, Rapunzel! Let down your hair to me.

Rapunzel had splendid hair, as fine as spun gold.positive, female

When the fairypositive, female called out, she untied it, wound it around a window hook, let it fall twenty yards to the ground,passive, female, neutral and the fairypositive, female climbed up it.active, female, eager

One day a youngneutral, male prince came through the forest where the tower stood.active, male, eager

He saw the beautifulpositive, female Rapunzel standing at her window, heard her sing with her sweet voice,positive, female and fell in love with her.passive, male, eager

Because there was no door in the tower and no ladder was tall enough to reach her, He came to the forest every day,active, male, eager until once he saw the fairy,positive, female who said:

Rapunzel, Rapunzel! Let down your hair.

Then he knew which ladder would get him into the tower.

He remembered the words that he would have to speak, and the next day, as soon as it was dark, he went to the tower and called upward:passive, male, eager

Rapunzel, Rapunzel! Let down your hair!

She let her hair fall.passive, female, eager He tied himself to it and was pulled up.active, male, eager

At first Rapunzel was frightened,negative, female but soon she came to like the young king so well that she arranged for him to come every day and be pulled up.passive, female, eager Thus they lived in joy and pleasure for a long time.

The fairypositive, female did not discover what was happening until one day Rapunzel said to her, "Frau Gothel, tell me why it is that my clothes are all too tight. They no longer fit me."

"You godless child,"negative, female said the fairy.positive, female "What am I hearing from you?" She immediately saw how she had been deceived and was terribly angry.negative, female

She took Rapunzel's beautifulpositive, female hair, wrapped it a few times around her left hand, grasped a pair of scissors with her right hand, and snip snip, cut it off.active, female, eager

Then she sent Rapunzel into a wildernessactive, female, eager where she suffered greatly and where, after a time, she gave birth to twins, a boy and a girl.passive, female, neutral

On the evening of the same day that she sent Rapunzel away, the fairypositive, female tied the cut-off hair to the hook at the top of the tower,active, female, eager and when the prince called out:

Rapunzel, Rapunzel! Let down your hair! she let down the hair.

The prince was startled to find the fairypositive, female instead of his belovedpositive, female Rapunzel.

"Do you know what, evilnegative, female one?" cried the angry fairynegative, female. "You have lost Rapunzel forever."

The prince, in his despair, threw himself from the tower.active, male, eager

He escaped with his life, but he lost his eyesight in the fall.

Sorrowfully he wandered about in the forest weeping and, eating nothing but grass and roots.passive, male, neutral

Some years later he happened into the wilderness where Rapunzel lived miserably with her children.passive, male, neutral

He thought that her voice was familiar.

She recognized him instantly as well and threw her arms around his neck.active, female, eager

Two of her tears fell into his eyes, and they became clear once again, and he could see as well as before.active, female, eager

Rapunzel (1857)

Once upon a time there was a man and a woman who had long, but to no avail, wished for a child. Finally the woman came to believe that the good Lord would fulfill her wish. Through the small rear window of these people's house they could see into a splendid garden that was filled with the most beautiful flowers and herbs. The garden was surrounded by a high wall, and no one dared enter, because it belonged to a sorceress who possessed great power and was feared by everyone.negative, female

One day the woman was standing at this window, and she saw a bed planted with the most beautiful rapunzel. It looked so fresh and green that she longed for some. It was her greatest desire to eat some of the rapunzel. This desire increased with every day, and not knowing how to get any, she became miserably ill.passive, female, eager

Her husband was frightenednegative, male, and asked her, "What ails you, dear wife?"

"Oh," she answered, "if I do not get some rapunzel from the garden behind our house, I shall die."

The man, who loved her dearly, thought, "Before you let your wife die, you must get her some of the rapunzel, whatever the cost."active, male, eager

So just as it was getting dark he climbed over the high wall into the sorceress'snegative, female garden, hastily dug up a handful of rapunzel, and took it to his wife.active, male, eager She immediately made a salad from it, which she devoured eagerly.active, female, eager It tasted so very good to her that by the next day her desire for more had grown threefold.If she were to have any peace, the man would have to climb into the garden once again.passive, female, hesitant Thus he set forth once againactive, male, eager just as it was getting dark. But no sooner than he had climbed over the wall than, to his horror, he saw the sorceressnegative, female standing there before him.

"How can you dare," she asked with an angry look,negative, female "to climb into my garden and like a thiefnegative, male to steal my rapunzel? You will pay for this."

"Oh," he answered, "Let mercy overrule justice. I came to do this out of necessity. My wife saw your rapunzel from our window, and such a longing came over her, that she would die, if she did not get some to eat."

The sorceress'snegative, female anger abated somewhat, and she said, "If things are as you say, I will allow you to take as much rapunzel as you want. >But under one condition: You must give me the child that your wife will bring to the world. It will do well, and I will take care of it like a mother."

In his fear the man agreed to everything.passive, male, hesitant

When the woman gave birth, the sorceressnegative, female appeared, named the little girl Rapunzel, and took her away. Rapunzel became the most beautifulpositive, female child under the sun. When she was twelve years old, the sorceressnegative, female locked her in a tower that stood in a forest and that had neither a door nor a stairway, but only a tiny little window at the very top.

When the sorceress wanted to enter, she stood below and called out:

Rapunzel, Rapunzel, Let down your hair to me.

Rapunzel had splendid long hair, as fine as spun gold.negative, female When she heard the sorceress'snegative, female voice, she untied her braids, wound them around a window hook, let her hair fall twenty yards to the ground, and the sorceress climbed up it.

A few years later it happened that a king's son was riding through the forest. As he approached the tower he heard a song so beautifulnegative, female that he stopped to listen. It was Rapunzel, who was passing the time by singing with her sweetpositive, female voice. The prince wanted to climb up to her, and looked for a door in the tower, but none was to be found.active, male, eager

He rode home, but the song had so touched his heart that he returned to the forest every day and listened to it.active, male, eager One time, as he was thus standing behind a tree, he saw the sorceress approach, and heard her say:

Rapunzel, Rapunzel, Let down your hair.

Then Rapunzel let down her strands of hair, and the sorceressnegative, female climbed up them to her.

"If that is the ladder into the tower,then sometime I will try my luck."active, male, eager

And the next day, just as it was beginning to get dark,he went to the tower and called out:active, male, eager

Rapunzel, Rapunzel, Let down your hair.

The hair fell down, and the prince climbed up.active, male, eager

At first Rapunzel was terribly frightenednegative, female when a man such as she had never seen before came in to her. However, the prince began talking to her in a very friendly manner,positive, male telling her that his heart had been so touched by her singing that he could have no peace until he had seen her in person.passive, male, eager Then Rapunzel lost her fear, and when he asked her if she would take him as her husband, she thought, He would rather have me than would old Frau Gothel." She said yes and placed her hand into his.active, female, neutral

She said, I would go with you gladly, but I do not know how to get down. Every time that you come, bring a strand of silk, from which I will weave a ladder. When it is finished I will climb down, and you can take me away on your horse."passive, female, eager They arranged that he would come to her every evening, for the old woman came by day.

The sorceressnegative, female did not notice what was happening until one day Rapunzel said to her, "Frau Gothel, tell me why it is that you are more difficult to pull up than is the young prince, who will be arriving any moment now?"

You godless child," cried the sorceress. "What am I hearing from you? I thought I had removed you from the whole world, but you have deceived me nonetheless."negative, female

In her anger she grabbed Rapunzel's beautifulpositive, female hair, wrapped it a few times around her left hand, grasped a pair of scissors with her right hand, and snip snap, cut it off. And she was so unmerciful that she took Rapunzel into a wilderness where she suffered greatly.

On the evening of the same day that she sent Rapunzel away, the sorceressnegative, female tied the cut-off hair to the hook at the top of the tower,active, female, eager and when the prince called out:

Rapunzel, Rapunzel, Let down your hair.

she let down the hair.passive, female, eager

The prince climbed up,positive, male but above, instead of his belovedpositive, female Rapunzel, he found the sorceressnegative, female, who peered at him with poisonousnegative, female and evilnegative, female looks.

"Aha!" she cried scornfully.negative, female "You have come for your Mistress Darling, but that beautiful birdpositive, female is no longer sitting in her nest, nor is she singing any more. The cat got her, and will scratch your eyes out as well. You have lost Rapunzel. You will never see her again."

The prince was overcome with grief, and in his despair he threw himself from the tower.active, male, hesitant He escaped with his life, but the thorns into which he fell poked out his eyes. Blind, he wandered about in the forest, eating nothing but grass and roots, and doing nothing but weeping and wailing over the loss of his beloved wife.positive, femalepassive, male, hesitant Thus he wandered about miserably for some years, finally happening into the wilderness where Rapunzel lived miserably with the twins that she had given birth to.passive, female, hesitantpassive, male, hesitant

He heard a voice and thought it was familiar. He advanced toward it, and as he approached, Rapunzel recognized him, and crying, threw her arms around his neck.passive, female, eager Two of her tears fell into his eyes, and they became clear once again, and he could see as well as before.passive, female, eager He led her into his kingdom, where he was received with joy, and for a long time they lived happily and satisfied.

A wild boar was wreaking havoc throughout the country. No one dared venture into the forest where it ran about. With its tusks it ripped to pieces anyone who was bold enough to pursue it and attempt to kill it. Then the king proclaimed that anyone who could kill the boar would receive his daughter for a wifeactive, male, eager.

There were three brothers in the kingdom. The oldestneutral, male was slynegative, male and clevernegative, male; the second was of ordinary intelligenceneutral, male; but the third and youngestneutral, male was innocentpositive, male and slow wittednegative, male. They wanted to win the princess, so they set forth to seek out the wild boar and kill itactive, male, eager.

The two oldestneutral, male ones went together, while the youngestneutral, male one went by himself. When he entered the woods an old man approached him. He was holding a black lance in his hand, and said to him, "Take this lance and fearlessly attack the boar with it, and you will kill it." And that is what happened. He struck the boar with the lance, and it fell dead to the earth. Then he lifted it onto his shoulder, and cheerfully set off toward homepassive, male, eager.

On the way he came to a house where his brothers were making merry and drinking wineactive, male, eager. When they saw him with the boar on his back, they called to him, "Come in and have a drink with us. You must be tired." The innocent simpletonnegative, male, not thinking about any danger, went inside and told them how he had killed the boar with the black lance, and rejoiced in his good fortunepassive, male, eager. That evening they returned home together. The two oldestneutral, male ones plotted to kill their brotheractive, male, eager. They let him walk ahead of thempassive, male, neutral, and when they came to a bridge just outside the city, they attacked him, striking him dead. They buried him beneath the bridgeactive, male, eager. Then the oldestneutral, male one took the boar, carried it to the king, claimed that he had killed itactive, male, eager, and received the princess for a wifepassive, female, eager.

Many years passed, but it was not to remain hidden. One day a shepherdneutral, male was crossing the bridge when he saw a little bone beneath him in the sandpassive, male, neutral. It was so pure and snow-white that he wanted it to make a mouthpiece from, so he climbed down and picked it up. Afterward he made a mouthpiece from it for his hornactive, male, eager, and when he put it to his lips to play, the little bone began to sing by itself:

Oh, dear shepherd You are blowing on my bone. My brothers struck me deadactive, male, eager, And buried me beneath the bridgeactive, male, eager, To get the wild boar For the daughter of the king.

The shepherd took the horn to the kingactive, male, eager, and once again it sang the same words. After hearing this, the king had his people dig under the bridge, and they soon uncovered the skeletonactive, male, eager. The two wickednegative, male brothers confessed their crimeactive, male, hesitant and were thrown into the waterpassive, male, hesitant. The murderedpassive, male, neutral brother's bones were laid to rest in a beautiful grave in the churchyardpassive, male, neutral.